okay we'll start the next
[Music]
section
um I'm also want to introduce a few
simulators that people nowadays are
using so the first one is MCO which is
uh very popular from from different
communities um I think I made a mistake
on the videos but essentially they are
they are physics engine that you can
simulate multi body and multi-objects
interactions so most of people in
robotics using the rigid body
interactions because that's relatively
fast and but mjo indeed so indeed can
simulate deformable objects and then
objects with different materials so
elasticities um that's a that's a pretty
like accurate
simulators so in recently they also have
updated versions uh which utilize GPU to
accelerate all the uh forward Dynamics
and contact detections so this is from
their official blogs so if you simulate
the original humanoid Jal using python
which is the default for many many RL
research uh is pretty slow and if you
have a lot of engineering effort you can
increase by increase that by a lot but
uh by using the GPU you can make it uh
significantly faster and provide a lot
of huge number of samples for your our
algorithms uh that's and um so next step
is something that is so I would say less
popular than Joo but is still very
important in the development of s to
real which is resim and brex so resim is
um is essentially a
parallel uh it's a parallel simulator
that written purely in C++ which
provides python interface and uh that's
the foundation of a lot of eth local
motion work that I also show in the uh
10 slides after that so brex is
another uh is another library that built
in ja and so they so the purpose of this
Z libraries to
study uh what to exactly study where you
have parallel simulated environments so
is that improve the performance of your
policy gradient Meers or like how F like
how how much it can
improve and there are also ISAC gy which
is a very critical for nowadays robot
learnings which um let me trying to
play so ISAC gam is you is produced by
Nvidia and of course naturally support
by Nvidia
gpus and what they can do is to simulate
10,000 or more than 10,000 of
environments and to doing different
tasks and the mo so I have been
personally switched so I have been uh
experiencing the pass from Dro to uh to
ISAC dream
so I think there are um in the paper
they claim that the speed is the most
important part I think speed is
definitely a huge advantage of Isa Drey
but for me the most like the most good
part is that I found if I want to make
some Jal or pipet another kind of CPU
library to be fast I need to utilize the
CPU as much as possible and this uh this
brings a problem actually so in our
laptop in our workstations or clusters
because these clusters is not
specifically for RL it's specifically
for neuron Network training so usually
there are maybe 10 gpus but the CPU is
not that good because if you consider
training neuron Network the CPU is not
heavily used compared to gpus so if I'm
going to open create some environment
libraries that can make mjo very fast I
can only run one experiments you know 8
GPU machine that's a huge
limitations but in ISO Drey because all
the things is naturally implemented in
GPU so the CPU utilization is actually
low and you can run um the same amount
of experiments as your GPU numbers so in
the context of deep learning RIS in the
context of using workstation build for
deep learning that's also a huge
advantage
um and of course there are problems of
using ISAC dream uh mainly coming from
you are using CPU you are using GPU to
solve all this you this contact
detections or contact
cions and one thing that may be not
considered before at least for me is
that in deep learning we always using
the float Point
arithmetics but uh so that's already
enough like empirically showing that you
can train in good neuron networks using
32 floating point but for physics
simulations so sometimes to resolve this
contact you also need higher precisions
which might be a reason that you will
find some unrealistic behaviors in Isa
dream that will not appear in some CPU
counterpart um okay and next we are also
going to talk talk
about uh RL plus s and what changes has
been made to make it work right
now um so the key of syt real success is
the idea of you have parallel
simulations you and you have the concept
called domain
randomizations so firstly remember
previously we were talking about RL
training is not stable and maybe it's
because at each time step the sample
trajectories is not enough to cover a
wide range of
distributions and but the this thing has
changed if you have a parallel
environment that can generate data
points at a significantly faster
speed so in the as gy examples it can
generate
maybe uh 10K oh actually 100K of
transitions at per second so you sudden
have 100K of like or equally amount of
batch size that can help you to optimize
your
policies and this number is of course
depending on how complex this
environments but it's definitely better
than you just have 200 badge size that
will make your policy trending not very
stable and there are also a challenge of
simeral Gap uh and the simal Gap is
caused by a lot of different factors so
for example in the physics
simulators we make a lot of assumptions
to make it run faster or maybe sometimes
to make it even feasible to run so for
example the objects is always being
convex fied and we do not have
continuous time in simulations we only
have discretized time and the body is
always rigid um I mean there are
there are simulators support the form of
objects but usually that's very
slow and there are also something called
column uh frictions which is not the not
the true frictions we will have in the
in the real world but some approximate
thing that you need to deal with when
you compare the uh when you consider the
contacts contact between two surface
instead of two
point so that's from the uh physics side
so which means no matter how good is
your simulators how much you invest that
into your invest into your simulators
it's really hard to make it as realistic
as the uh physics as the physics in the
real
world on the other hand there is also an
perspective of photo realistic sensors
is also very hard to simulate so we have
very Advanced Techniques in graphics or
animations and of course we can simulate
very realistic uh scenes so this is from
a movie called Jungle Book but if you
look at like the cost of generating this
kind of SCS is obviously not suitable
for training robotics uh
agents and it turns out of course we can
simplify this process but the results is
what we actually use in simulation some
environment looks like this so it's not
bad but it's definitely not realistic so
if you are training some models here
it's not going to be transferable to
real world
policies and so this comes to the idea
of domain randomizations both in terms
of visions and
physics so the idea of domain
randomization is essentially so domains
me which is like the distribution either
in your simulation so in in the real
world and you are going to randomize the
distributions from different
aspects so the idea is in the training
time we are going
to um randomize a lot of things we can
do and most specifically this case for
example the background colors and the uh
the the the the color of the desktop
all the camera angles or camera
specifications like extrinsic intrinsic
Matrix and for that to training some
either policy or your vision
detectors and the idea is really if the
models is of enough simulated variations
the real world may just look like
another
simulators and we are not we are always
not seeking to uh finding something that
is as similar as the T time but we are
hoping we are hopefully that some part
of the
simulators at one of the environment is
similar enough to the test scene that is
in the real
world and this is for the visual part
and there are also um from the Dynamics
part which so this is a simple I guess
uh this is should be a s s simple
pushing task that training from
simulation to the real world so in the
simulation training for each of the
rout uh the authors actually sample a
different set of physical parameters
which shows here um the resolution is
kind of a little bit slow but
essentially the robot Mass the the mass
of the robot link and also different
controller parameters such as joint
dampings all the mass of the all the
mass of the objects friction of the
objects so all of them are kind of
randomized in simulation training and
when you deploy in the real world so you
can imagine the environment has already
been seen as a combination of all these
randomized
parameters so taking it maybe visually
is that if you consider you have a not
randomized simulation data it covers a
little bit of distributions but the real
world distribution is much larger than
that so sometimes even your uncalibrated
models is have no overlap compared to
the real world data and the idea of
domain randomization is to saying I'm
going
to um increaseing the coverage of this
data not by looking at how Sim not
trying to exactly replicate the real
world data but simply expand the
boundaries of that uh simulated data to
achieve a larger set of domain
randomizations and if a policy achieves
good performance on these larger green
regions it will tend to uh achieve also
good policies it also be a good policies
in the real world
distributions okay any
questions and
finally in this section we are also
going to talk about a few success
examples of Sy real and domain
randomizations and see how they are
going to like um evidence how how the
previous sections know knowledge or
techniques apply to these
examples so this first example is from
openi uh first de first hand work before
they are doing T GPT they also doing
robotics so the the task here is you
have a robot hand and you are
manipulating this Cube so that it become
the same orientations as specified by
this
scod and this task is significantly very
is
challenging if you if you if you're not
doing that using RL and the reason is
because um and the reason is because
there are too many contact and different
types of contact between your robot
manipulators and the cube so if you are
doing a traditional control MPC based
meth the search space is is quite huge
and so basically you have each joint
each joint have a binary number so if
you only consider binary contact each
joint can have a binary contact of the
objects and all the possible so you have
maybe 26 joint you then you have two to
the power of
26 and this is very hard search problems
and previous control based methods
cannot do
that and um this extremely complicated
recovery task was successful and this is
another work from eth uh where they are
they are doing simal
for uh learning these robot recovery
behaviors so you have this robots that
falling down on the ground from
different configurations and is trying
to stand up this is maybe from 2018 or
2019 that also by the same logic the
challenge here is that there are too
many contact that not only using the uh
only the tip of the food to make these
recoveries so you also need to use other
part of your body to make this recovery
so if you consider that from from a
planning with contact perspectives
this is very hard to write or to solve
these
optimizations um and another
examples which
is um from which is from our forward
bommer labm they are trying to do drone
racings that can beat human
Champions so this so in this case is not
the challenge here is not exactly
because of the contact
instead it's actually because when you
have a very small drones and operate in
a very high speed pushing the limits of
joint
torqus affected by this uh this high
resistance force so the physics model
here is very hard to write so so this is
not uh this is not the same as when you
consider most of the physics you can
ignore the resistance of air but in this
case you need to consider that and
that's fit is very
physically uh challenging to write the
equations but in s you can do something
to achieve
this sorry can I say it
again
oh uh yes so let me pause
this so so this is real time and there
are two
drones um sorry the videos is let me
trying to stop here so there are two
drones I think this drone is controlled
by reinforced learning controllers and
this one is controlled by a human
champion and they are doing this this
racing you you a very large Stadium uh
that the the target is to you you cross
these doors in a sequential order and we
like whoever doing that fastest is
win and is the input to the Drone like
is it video algb video or is it it's
it's rgbd camera
input yes but there are some uh so the
polic I I so if I remember correctly the
policy does not directly take RGB but
they estimate some uh positions of where
is the door
but the human will so the human re human
Reser will wear a VR device that also
received the first person view of the
Drone so the human is not from third
person it's also from like the the
viewing angle of the
Drone oh
yes so there is a slower Replay that
each of the drones need to pass
different doors and this is the humans
Viewpoint and this is just from other
captures no um so the so this one the
obstacle is always fixed but uh yes yes
so the r algorithms is training on the
exactly same obstacles but the humans is
also like have a lot of time to get
familiar with this this uh
setup
and uh for simp real there are also a
lot of success in Locomotion and de
source manipulations so the majority of
the content will be uh discussed in the
in the later lectures on case studies on
these two separate
topics and essentially um how to bridge
the S to real Gap is in in all of
these like successful videos I have
shown is kind of maybe three very
important concept the first one is you
need to have a proper system
identification which is sort of a
requirement so the system identification
is essentially saying your robot system
where you command it to do the same
thing in simulation and real world so if
you give the same action command for
your robot in simulation and in the real
world you want the response of the robot
to be the same so otherwise it's very
hard to transfer if this is not even
close and the domain randomization we
have just uh illustrate a little bit and
also uh we also need to find the correct
abstraction mainly from the vision uh
perspectives so I will give some of the
example in in this so for example this
is uh this is the examples of how the
openi turn their reorientation policies
trying to manipulate the cube to be a
specific
post so firstly they need to have a like
a large amount of parallel environments
because they need to collect huge amount
of data like billions in the scale of
billions level billions number
samples uh to make their policies to be
to make their policy training
stable
um and in this case what they use is
actually exactly almost the same as we
talk about is the p is the P
algorithms and on the other hand it also
need a lot of parallel environments
because it need to do a lot of
randomizations so if you consider your
large batch of data you you also need to
um want the policy to be robust to so
you simultaneously want your policy
robust to all kinds of different
physical environment but you also want
your policy when when when you optimize
the policy you also want the data to
cover a lot of distributions so this
tool is gives it requires you to get a
significantly large amount of badge
sizes um and the physical randomization
they have is also so very aggressive so
as you can see the test set is
actually um the same Cube um across all
the different runs so one hypothesis
like where you initially trying to
develop some systems you might want to
just doing the exact trying to simulate
the exactly same Cube uh from the simil
from the real world like to make them
the same as in the real world and
simulation but this actually not quite
works well because so there are a lot of
different reasons so for
example uh the limitation of
simulations it exactly tells
you even if you define the physical
parameters such as mass frictions to be
the same the Dynamics of the objects
might not be the same as in the real
world because of a lot of simplification
we made mentioned in the
slice and
also there are also limited number of
physical parameters you can Define in
simulation so although there are like
the most important like Mass friction
Center of mass you can modify that
Define that in the simulator but there
are also some other things maybe the
elasticity is not quite perfect um
reflected in the simulations and there
are lots of un model effects
where you where you consider the Sim to
row transfer so even though they end up
using the same robot Cube but they still
need to do a large amount of domain
randomizations on the objects so for
example the objects Dimensions the size
of the objects need to be changed the
mass of the objects and also the robot
link also need to be changed also uh
frictions and controller parameters
also um Act parameters Al even the
gravities also need to be changed so all
this the purpose of all this is to cover
a wide range of distributions so that in
your real world you hopefully in the
real world transitions Dynamics is
falling on some set of this uh this
randomized
Dynamics uh yeah this is some
yeah oh
and apart from these physical domain
randomizations there are also a lot of
small things you need to
randomize um so for
example when you deploy your algorithms
in the real world the sensings you
received from the robot is really not
perfect so if a robot tell tells you the
joint now is 90° it doesn't necessarily
be
90° and when you control the robot to be
I'm saying is going to this robot joint
rotate to 100 Dee is also tell so
sometimes it tells you is 100 degree but
there are also some small errors that
always happens in the hardw and then in
this case a natural idea to extend the
domain randomization which is you can
add a lot of observation noise um like
the joint positions or object positions
on that and also there are also action
delays um when you apply when you send
some command to your robot is not
immediately sent uh there are also some
random delay that maybe 10 millisec so
depending on the robot 10 millisecond 20
millisecond it's also not a fixed number
of milliseconds to get that and uh so
that's another thing and also there are
also some very tedious but important typ
important step like
randomize um what is the time step of
your simulations so simulations
essentially you divide each simulation
times so
you uh you integrate all the velocities
at a certain time intervals and you also
need to randomize that so what is so
whether is 100 millisecond or 10
milliseconds and there are also some
like Rob robot specific maybe backlash
or uh some random Force onto the object
so there are lot of huge amount of
things you need to randomize to make it
work so that's all from the physical and
observational um thing and there are
another aspect which we briefly talk
about the simulation images is really
different from the real world images and
if if we directly training a policy take
RGB images that's are likely to work so
what rely on uh for all this sorial work
is to finding some something we called
abstractions so you're are going to find
some abstraction that although the rgbd
images is not RGB images is not the same
between them and real and we hope the
abstractions can be the same from SIM
through and in the case of open I xess
hand what they have is the object post
so they have essentially training object
so so firstly they have three cameras
from different from different viewing
angles and they from the simulation data
they randomize a lot of different colors
or textures of either the robot or the
environments together with the lighting
scenarios and they have these three
Hamas uh three RGB images and output
object post of the
objects and in this case it's only a
single Cube
so this post estimation is actually not
very easy especially especially when you
consider all the inclusions you have for
uh this inhand manipulation scenarios
and this probably is
the um so if you only consider one
single object this may be the best way
you can get for post
estimation and finally like in the final
deployment of their robot
policy they firstly have a state
estimator from images and the images
will be merged to become some object
Po and so this is so this is important
because when you consider the policy
trainings in simulations so it only
receives the objects Po and the finger
so objects post fingertip positions
together with other states that is
physically meaningful so it gets rid of
all the rendering not realistic
rendering effect and only consider some
quantities that is very close from SIM
to real and that's why it can work
otherwise if you go into TR Vision
policy that's will be significantly
amount of other work to transfer it from
SIM to
real um so this is one examples but this
examples might be very limited because
so firstly defining the object's post is
very limited and if you have another
objects it will be also limited um so
this process meter is not going to work
for more complex uh
objects so another examples is from
the oh yeah
so they have three cameras viewing the
cube from three different angles and
they are
having I I think it should be three
separate networks I kind of forget and
then this is merging these three
informations into one to have predict
what is object
posst I think it's just
concatenations yeah
uh yeah and there is also question if
you think about what if you don't have
the concept of object post so for
example on another task which is this
drone racing task you can see the Drone
is flying in the wild with no concept of
objects so you cannot represent leaves
and trees as objects
and but they can still do that by using
syn Rail and finding some abstra correct
abstractions between simulators and the
real world and in this case their
abstraction is the depth
images
um most specifically if you consider
this is the simulators they used um or
training their policies so and this is
in the real world deployment what the
camera has seen in the in the robot
drawn so this two is very hard between
this simulation and real word it would
be very hard to transfer from SIM to
real even if you have a lot of
randomizations um so what's what the
authors actually do is to have a
simulated depth that trying to mimic
what is happens in the real
world so if you look at the depths of
the this is some um modified D STS from
the simulator but is also U comes from
the simulators so if you look at the
deps images and the real world images so
although they are not exactly the same
but the physical meaningness of each
pixel is actually pretty much the same
because you can relatively accurate
simulate how the camera formation how
the image formation Works in simulation
and in the real world Guided by your
computer vision class there is some 3D
projections onto the image
plane um and this is how they Bridge the
simt real Gap not using the RGB images
but using the
deps uh coming from like using the deps
from simulations and trying to match
that to be the same as real
words and this work also have another
aspect um to be like completely to
describe this works so you do not need
to combine RL together with Sim so SIM
can also be together used by another set
of things so for example in
simulation the advantage of simulation
if you remember is we have all the
states informations of the environments
so it would be easy to have have um
would be easy to write a planning
algorithm or even a sampling algorithms
that sample some desired trajectories
for the Drone to uh to finish so in this
case for example in their case is you
want to have a drone from point A to
point B but the most important thing is
you want to avoid all the collisions and
in this case you have all the
informations about trace and simulations
you can generate a trajectories by
simply sample along this different
trajectories and this is your like kind
of expert policy that is a very good
policy uh in
simulations and what we need to do
here is trying to find some way to get
supervision from this expert policy
using only the depth images so the upper
part the policy receives a lot of so all
the trade informations all the ground
for State informations but it turns we
can use only the measurement from um
only simple measurements such as
IMU uh internal state of the drones all
the camera or single rgbd cam cameras
attached on the Drone to mimic the uh
the performance of the expert
policies and this is how they uh
achieved this in the wild Jone
racings um shown in the previous video
and this work is from the very beginning
I shown this um you are going to so
there is a drone racing winning the
world champions and the way they do that
is still trying to do s real um so in
this time is trying to consider RL
algorithms
um so it's kind of not too many things
so we just so in the previous work you
can replace this by reinforcement
learning algorithms because now your
task is slightly more complex than
following trajectories uh to and avoid
condition conditions you also need to
follow a specific order to pass through
this stores and in this fixed
environment R is performs very
good and the main difference in this
work is
actually what authors observed when you
want to uh push the limits to a to a
extreme so instead of only using Sim so
simil basically you get some models and
then leave that Al uh in the real world
no matter what happens you does not
change the weight but in this case one
important part is they also collect some
data in the real world so after you get
this policy
performs give some reasonable
performance in the real world you can
you can have some receive you can get
some feedback from The Real World
deployment to improve improve your
simulations so for example one simple
way to do that is you deploy your
algorithms and then you record the
trajectories in the real world and then
you check the difference between the
real world and in the simulations and
there must be a difference between the
uh because there is a s real cap but
what you could do is you could learning
in these models from SIM real that in
the next round of training when you're
training in simulators you're actually
applying the physics in the simulator
and add the residual physics you learned
from Real World to that and in this case
your model essentially learning on a
dynamics that is closer to the real
world Dynamics although that's still not
going to be perfectly aligned but this
will improve the performance by a large
margin um um so that's
essentially and in this case of course
the abstraction becomes even simpler
because they can there is some onboard
detection methods very light fight
neuron Network running to detect where
is the gate so also the gates have some
markers here so that's relatively simple
compared to uh using compared to the
inal forest
perceptions but still that's also gives
a flavor gives you a flavor of they
still need abstractions for their policy
to do s real instead of taking directly
the rgbd images of U to accomplish these
tasks okay and this is my last slid and
any questions
okay I guess very luckily we can end up
earlier this this
time
um yes I guess many I guess there are M
questions about midterm and I also don't
know maybe next week uh when J hund come
back you can ask him